<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="playtypusgames.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="playtypusgames.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-19T13:26:59-05:00</updated><id>playtypusgames.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PlaytypusGames</title><subtitle>We are here to make good Games</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Playtypus Experiment #2</title><link href="playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/19/The-Playtypus-Experiment-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Playtypus Experiment #2" /><published>2024-02-19T13:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-19T13:00:00-05:00</updated><id>playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/19/The-Playtypus-Experiment-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/19/The-Playtypus-Experiment-2.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="progress-report">Progress Report</h2>

<p>This last month, Inno &amp; I have been working ass on a few topics :</p>

<p>Inno :</p>
<ul>
  <li>Onboarding on the project</li>
  <li>Learning about Shaders</li>
  <li>Learning about ECS &amp; Dots</li>
  <li>Learning about UI Toolkit</li>
  <li>Helped a Lot with the conveyor placement logic</li>
  <li>Starting a skeleton of UI &amp; Experimenting &amp; iterating on a lot of Ideas for it.</li>
  <li>Worked on the conveyor Flow to add some conditions on how they should be placed.</li>
</ul>

<p>Touhma :</p>
<ul>
  <li>Finishing the base for the framework for the factory stuff ( Recipes , Buildings, Items )</li>
  <li>With long talks with Inno refactored the entire conveyor building logic to make it easier to work with</li>
  <li>A lot of optimisation on critical part of the code ( Items on Belts etc … )</li>
  <li>Refactoring of the codebase in progress to reduce garbage code &amp; reduce the complexity of the project</li>
  <li>Merging codebase of utilitary customs libraries with our project code base &amp; add AssemblyDefinitions to split the codebase into bittable chunks</li>
</ul>

<p>The foundations are there and we are making sure that we can confortably add more features in the long run.</p>

<p>We had to take some time too to make sure we were globaly on the same page with the project as we are going to work together on long run on that.</p>

<h1 id="a-story-about-conveyors---part-2">A story about Conveyors - Part 2</h1>

<h3 id="1---satisfactory-like">1 - Satisfactory Like</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>So ? what did you decide to go with ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>With all the kind of solutions we thought about, given the scale of the game we want to make we went with a very satisfactory-like method of building conveyors.</p>

<p><img src="../assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/ConveyorBelt.png" alt="img.png" /></p>

<p>Note the blue &amp; orange arrow , this is important for later.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>that’s it ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Patience ! All assets that you are going to see are basically work in progress &amp; temporary assets, We are still looking for someone to help us in that department !</p>

<p>Sooooo we decided on , for multiples reasons, to go with a belt that is based on a spline. ( cf <a href="https://playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-1.html">TPE#1</a>) 
It is designed to be simple but flexible for a lot of usecases we have in mind for the game. 
We spend quite a fair amount of time to get it right.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What about the arrows ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So here is a thing, for the belt here are the ground rules :</p>
<ul>
  <li>A belt can be build ONLY between “sockets” .</li>
  <li>A belt can have a starting point &amp; an end point.</li>
  <li>A belt can’t have a socket on it’s own.</li>
  <li>The spline is the thing that, later, will be saved on the save file, not the mesh.</li>
  <li>The mesh is dynamically generated between these points by the client.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Still don’t answer my question … And … A socket ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A Socket is basically going to be one point that accept a belt. 
Each building that have stuff to do with belt is going to have at least one socket on them.
And a socket can be of 2 types :</p>

<p>Input : 
<img src="../assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/InputSocket.png" alt="InputSocket" /></p>

<p>Or Output : 
<img src="../assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/OutputSocket.png" alt="OutputSocket" /></p>

<p>Asset Temporary, remember ?</p>

<p>And because the belt can’t have sockets on it</p>

<p>We are going full on satisfactory on that ( remember to play that gem, it’s great ) we want to introduce you to …</p>

<p><img src="../assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/ConveyorPole.png" alt="ConveyorPole" /></p>

<p>Basically a simple building with 2 sockets : an Input &amp; an Output.</p>

<p>Here is how it look at the begining of the belt :</p>

<p><img src="../assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/BeltInput.png" alt="BeltInput" /></p>

<p>And when you build it :</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://playtypusgames.github.io/assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/ConveyorBeltsShowcase.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p>Note that you do have two poles In that example.</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://playtypusgames.github.io/assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/ConveyorBeltsShowcase2.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p>The system is flexible enough to actually just care if you are connected to a socket or not &amp; we do have an API allowing us to get more information from there, after.</p>

<p>We are going to show more in the nexts following blogs</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Wait but do the belts do … the thing ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What thing ?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You know … The thing …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That ?</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://playtypusgames.github.io/assets/Images/PlaytypusExperiment/%232/ConveyorBeltsShowcase3.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<blockquote>
  <p>Yes !</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Welp , obviously … that’s going to be the whole theme of the game …</p>

<p>On that note.</p>

<p>Don’t forget to join <a href="https://discord.gg/sXrYTmXekC">Our Brand new Discord</a> to learn more about the project , share your comment in the forum space there &amp; tutti frutti !</p>

<p>Take care everyone and see you next week !</p>

<p>Touhma</p>]]></content><author><name>Touhma</name></author><category term="Belts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Progress Report]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Playtypus Experiment #1</title><link href="playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Playtypus Experiment #1" /><published>2024-02-12T17:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T17:00:00-05:00</updated><id>playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="playtypusgames.github.io/belts/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-1.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="a-story-about-conveyors---part-1">A story about Conveyors - Part 1</h1>

<h2 id="the-beginning">The Beginning</h2>

<p>Here is the thing … I love conveyor belts in a games as much as I love automation Games in general. So it was only natural for me to build a game that is an automation game.
I want to learn in the process as much as possible, reproduce what worked, improve what did not or what , as a player was bothering me.
I spent countless hours in games like <a href="https://www.factorio.com/">Factorio</a>, <a href="https://www.satisfactorygame.com/">Satisfactory</a>, <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1366540/Dyson_Sphere_Program/">Dyson Sphere Program</a>. More recently I even play the rought  diamond that is <a href="https://techtonicagame.com/">Techtonica</a> !</p>

<p>In all these game you have by a way or another conveyor belts serving as the main gameplay element. It’s like hypnosis and satisfaction boost when you are looking at your factory and that it work. ( Either that or it trigger your OCD and you restart the game 5 times to get it just right … )
They come in different Shapes , Forms, have multiples gameplay mechanics around it &amp; it’s always fun to see what Developers come up with when it’s coming to a piece so central to a game.</p>

<p>The main function of a belt is to transport an object from point A to point B. This is the core.</p>

<p>Seems simple, right ? I was thinking that and oh boy I was wrong …</p>

<h3 id="1---the-case-of-a-codemonkey">1 - The case of a CodeMonkey</h3>

<p>When I started researching on the topic I ended up on a video from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=88cIVR4KI_Q">CodeMonkey</a> .</p>

<p>( If you still don’t know him, please check him out he is a great code explainer and I definitely learned a LOT from his videos )</p>

<p>Here is how it looks like at the end of the video :
<img src="https://imgur.com/zLtdyo2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>It looks good, works and do the job. And sometimes it’s all we ask.
It constantly checks the spaces on the next belts and then move the item from A to B.</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://i.imgur.com/WbwPNDm.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p>Each belt is occupying one tile and is regular allowing for a convenient way to place the belt, a model that is repeated and easily customisable.</p>

<h3 id="2---the-factory-must-grow">2 - The factory Must Grow</h3>

<p>Here is the thing either you are in 2D or in 3D , if you can get a regular grid it’s easy once you figure out how to move the items from a belt to an another.
The belt is the size of a tile in a squared grid, Exactly like in Factorio ( 2D , A tile ) &amp; Techtonica ( 3D , A cube )</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/NvTYu01.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>source : <a href="https://www.factorio.com/blog/post/fff-269">FFF-269</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do they have to plan ahead for all combinations possibles ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Huuuuh kinda, You can optimise and rotate the sprites, but you still have to make the sprites &amp; animate them &amp; all  :</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/e1uA3eZ.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>source : <a href="https://www.factorio.com/blog/post/fff-269">FFF-269</a></p>

<p>But this is it for the similarities. They spend a LOT of time optimising that part of the game.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Isn’t that a bit overkill ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In any factory builder with belts, it’s the main building you are gonna make. so you can end up with thousands of them.
If the code behind is slow it can become your main bottleneck &amp; steal some precious fps from your dear players.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/NVlG9As.gifv" alt="" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Yeah so in the end they do like the Codemonkey prototype approach to move the items ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Welp … while it’s a tile approach for the visual… In Reality to move the items they split the belts paths into Segments.</p>

<p><img src="https://imgur.com/2plFELR.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>source : <a href="https://www.factorio.com/blog/post/fff-176">FFF-176</a></p>

<p>Then they save the distance value between each item and move the items accordingly. It results in a way more scalable &amp; optimized way of doing that.</p>

<p>Another core difference is that 1 belt can carry 2 lines of items &amp; it’s part of their design so 1 belt = in reality 2 lines so it’s even more important to optimize here.
As far as i know they are the only one to do it this way and that’s their identity point ! ( at least , one of them ) and some game mechanics are built around that simple key fact.</p>

<p>Now that’s good and all but these two have a very regular grid to work with.
What happen when you don’t have a perfectly squared grid ?</p>

<h3 id="3---its-not-fair-i-need-to-sleep">3 - It’s not fair I need to sleep</h3>

<p>You get Dyson Sphere Program .
The game is happening , instead of a flat surface, on the surface of a sphere. Making a game usable grid on a sphere is … HARD, I read a LOT of papers on the topic and it’s complex.
So they did not bother trying to do it.
Instead, they use a special grid type that I’ll present to you in another blog post later.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/AOt7vsH.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>But even then they managed to have belts working :</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/V1ByAUw.png" alt="" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Alright, what’s the catch ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>First, they don’t follow the previous rule of 1 belt per grid square. When you look closely you can see they get the point between the lines of the grid, not at the middle of the square.</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://i.imgur.com/slugQGM.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<blockquote>
  <p>Another DevLog I suppose ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yup, and that is not as straightforward as it sound :D but it works.</p>

<p>Lucky for me, having created &amp; worked on the <a href="https://dsp.thunderstore.io/package/Galactic_Scale/GalacticScale/">GalacticScale Mod</a> for the game I digged into their code base for, and I’m familiar with how they did it …</p>

<p>As you can see in the video : each belt have small segments you can modify the segments, delete each belt individually.</p>

<p>In the background, like Factorio &amp; Satisfactoy ( foreshadowing ) they have a way to create some sort of dynamic graph that contain all the segments of the factory to move the items along the lines.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But how do they PLACE the conveyors ?
The grid look a bit messy, did they made models for each differences in alignment &amp; curvature of the sphere ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Welp I’m glad you asked !</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Give me a break …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I refuse ! Soooooo …
First of all , have look :</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://i.imgur.com/KEgzAgj.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p>See the differences ?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Very clear indeed …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As said previously the first difference is that the build point is on the intersection of the lines.
Not in the cell.
This allows the devs to do something in between these points &amp; to bend the line created in between these points. They create a path for all the line crossing they encounter ( That will be a topic for another dedicated DevLog )</p>

<h3 id="4---the-green-yellow-line">4 - The <del>Green</del> Yellow Line</h3>

<p>It turns out that to make conveyor belt that bend ( lol ) to you will you need a little mathematical something ! The secret sauce turns out to be something called a <a href="[Bézier curve - Wikipedia](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9zier_curve)">bezier curve</a> between each points.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A what ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A Bezier is basically the representation of a line, not necessarily straight but could be. Imagine train tracks, you have the start , the end , and the path is not always a straight line.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Alright …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can represent any kind of shapes you want for your conveyors with Bezier Curves.
Once they have this, they can generate the mesh along the “spline” relatively easily.</p>

<p>And one of the advantage of a spline is that it’s easy to evaluate where an item is on it. So what’s happening is that the code do the same as for factorio : the items on the belt follow the spline &amp; some dedicated code take care of handling the transfert of items between the belts segments when different but connected.</p>

<p>Here is a nice tool to play with a Bezier and see how it works : <a href="[Bezier (acegikmo.com)](https://acegikmo.com/bezier/)">Bezier</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Still don’t know what a Spline is … You are Confusing …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While a Bezier Curve is a representation of … a curve, ( yeah I know … ), a Spline is basically a group of these curves with some control points.
Just as a note you don’t have to do a Bezier to represent a line, but it’s the most commonly used.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Why ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Because.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thank you …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You are Welcome !  , nah I mean it’s really a “simple” way of representing any kind of path, and except if you are certain that your game will ever only have straight lines, you want to represent theses curves.</p>

<p>Here is a representation in DSP :</p>

<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/UZ5vNdj.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>cf : Look at the yellow interval.</p>

<p>A spline is Basically a list of Bezier Curves ( cf : orange line ) so it’s the curve between A &amp; B - B &amp; C - C &amp; D etc …</p>

<p>Once the spline is calculated the game save that, generate the meshes ( one for each Beziers curves ) along the spline &amp; then forget about it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Wow, Slow Down …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Future DevLog !</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Okey !</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="5---thanks-jace-snutt--help-a-lot-">5 - Thanks <del>Jace</del> Snutt ! Help a Lot !</h3>

<p>And where is all of that bringing us to ? Welp, to the last contender of this list : Satisfactory</p>

<video width="100%" autoplay="autoplay" loop="true" muted="">
  <source src="https://i.imgur.com/V22vdgX.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<blockquote>
  <p>What am I supposed to see ?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No grids at all , Just two point gracefully joining to create a belt out of thin air.</p>

<p>When you compare it with DSP another key difference is that when you place a belt it’s a segment that you are placing. You can’t divide ( well , yes but not the same way ) it by removing a piece of it without removing the entire belt.</p>

<p>Gosh I love this game. Play it if you have not !</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sure Seeing the time it’s going to take for your game anyway …</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Anyway !</p>

<p>This is the different belts type that i’m aware of that are out there in games you can play today.</p>

<p>We have :</p>
<ul>
  <li>The sprite Belt that transport item From itself to it’s neighbor</li>
  <li>The sprite Belt that do that with a segment</li>
  <li>The Spline Belt that split up the belt in smaller segments</li>
  <li>The spline belt that consider a belt as a huge segments</li>
</ul>

<p>Each type have pros &amp; cons &amp; different gameplay possibilities.</p>

<p>In the next DevLog, we are going to keep digging in that topic, and I’m about to reveal the solution will be used in the game we chose for the prototype of the game.</p>

<p>Until then, you can join <a href="https://discord.gg/sXrYTmXekC">Our Brand new Discord</a> to learn more about the project :</p>

<p>Take care and keep building belts !</p>

<p>Touhma</p>]]></content><author><name>Touhma</name></author><category term="Belts" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A story about Conveyors - Part 1]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Playtypus Experiment #0</title><link href="playtypusgames.github.io/announcements/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-0.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Playtypus Experiment #0" /><published>2024-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>playtypusgames.github.io/announcements/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-0</id><content type="html" xml:base="playtypusgames.github.io/announcements/2024/02/12/The-Playtypus-Experiment-0.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="so-it-begin-">So It Begin …</h1>

<h2 id="what-is-this-game-about-">What is this game about ?</h2>

<h3 id="short-version">Short Version</h3>

<p>A factory game in space.</p>

<h3 id="longer-version">Longer Version</h3>

<p>Nothing being set in stone YET as we are still early in the project what I can share for now is that the game will take inspirations from a little bit of everywhere.</p>

<h3 id="the-main-offender">The main Offender</h3>
<p><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1366540/Dyson_Sphere_Program/">Dyson Sphere Program</a></p>

<p><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/steam/apps/1366540/ss_1f699b2ba7ce5025064050cf5498f6a576b89d31.1920x1080.jpg?t=1702624498" alt="Dyson Sphere Program" /></p>

<p>The idea of sprawling factories has always appealed to me, and it’s the first game that was doing it at a scale that gave us the impressions that the planets were ours
First of all , this is the kind of scale we are aiming at…</p>

<h3 id="the-contenders">The Contenders</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.factorio.com/">Factorio</a>
<img src="https://cdn.factorio.com/assets/img/artwork/rocket-man.png" alt="Factorio" /></p>

<p>First game in the entry that gave me this Automation obsession and triggered so many bitter alerts in my bases</p>

<p><a href="https://www.satisfactorygame.com/">Satisfactory</a>
<img src="https://a.storyblok.com/f/110098/1920x1080/24abf6040e/u8_1920x1080_nologo.png" alt="Satisfactory" /></p>

<p>Second game in the genre that gave me sleepless night but at the same time show a very impressive building system</p>

<p><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1113120/IXION/">IXION</a>
<img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/steam/apps/1113120/ss_236f68d8b1a0c891b401689fcd0e9030f6550b74.1920x1080.jpg?t=1701947072" alt="IXION" /></p>

<p>Ixion was my big surprise of the last year. The soundtrack is amazing &amp; the style of the game is gorgeous.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn.akamai.steamstatic.com/steam/apps/1113120/ss_1e633861f899ece1221ce6da6c892a9a706ac359.1920x1080.jpg?t=1701947072" alt="IXION" /></p>

<p>And honestly that bad boy is Incredible.</p>

<h3 id="what-will-differentiate-us-from-them-">What will differentiate us from them ?</h3>

<p>We are still exploring ideas, we will iterate on mechanics that will make us unique …</p>

<p>That will be explained and communicated in the future blogs. 
For now We are working hard on the technicals challenges we are facing. So you will have to be patient to see what we are doing.</p>

<p>What have already been communicated :</p>
<ul>
  <li>Planetary building in a similar way than of Dyson Sphere Program</li>
  <li>Multiplayer is a “We want it” item on our todo list while not yet being worked on we are building the game with this in mind and the code is made so we will start implementation on that front soon™</li>
  <li>Factory &amp; automation is going to be core</li>
  <li>spaghetti ?</li>
</ul>

<p>Speaking of ! In the next DevLog, we are going to talk about spaghetti.</p>

<p>Until then, you can join <a href="https://discord.gg/sXrYTmXekC">Our Brand new Discord</a> to learn more about the project, chat, share ideas &amp; meet the dev team !</p>

<p>Touhma</p>]]></content><author><name>Touhma</name></author><category term="Announcements" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So It Begin …]]></summary></entry></feed>